Guide to the American Theological Library Association Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
American Theological Library Association Records
1945-1997
RG 163
Yale University Divinity School Library
63
138 boxes
This record group includes organizational and administrative records, board and committee records, materials from annual conferences, and ATLA publications. The American Theological Library Association was founded in 1947 to strengthen ties among theological libraries, to support theological and religious librarianship, to improve theological libraries, and to interpret the role of libraries in theological education.
American Theological Library Association
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the American Theological Library Association
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1947 Jun First national conference of seminary librarians held at Louisville Presbyterian Seminary with fifty librarians in attendance. A permanent organization was created by adopting a name, tentative constitution, and a slate of officers with an executive committee.
1947 Committee on Religious Periodical Indexing appointed
1948 Periodical exchange program initiated
1949 Committee on Microphotography appointed
1950-1952 Joint Committee of ATLA and American Association of Theological School drafted revised accreditation standards
1951 Committee on Cataloging and Classification appointed
1952 Committee on Religious Periodical Indexing coordinated a cooperative effort of twenty libraries to do indexing. First volume of Index to Religious Periodical Literature edited by Stillson Judah
1953 ATLA newsletter created; Donn Michael Farris served as editor for thirty-nine years
1956 ATLA received grant from Sealantic Fund to support microtext and indexing programs
1957 Board of Microtext organized, with Raymond P. Morris as chair (retired in 1972), assisted by his wife Jean as volunteer office staff. Six serials were filmed in 1958. By 1965 over 150,000 linear feet of microfilm had been produced, utilizing the facilities at the University of Chicago Department of Photoduplication.
1957 Index Board organized, with Jannette Newhall as chair and Lucy W. Markley as editor (1957-1959).
1959-1968 Grants received from Lilly Foundation to improve education qualifications of theological librarians.
1960 Calvin Schmitt appointed chair of Index Board (retired in 1979) and G. Fay Dickerson employed as full-time indexer and office manager. Members of Index Board had editorial oversight of Index until 1965 when Dickerson was appointed editor (retired in 1983)
1961-1963 Grants received from Sealantic Fund to support the Library Development Program, a program designed to strengthen the book collections of libraries.
1961 Committee on Reprinting organized to coordinate reprint of scarce titles
1962 First report of Committee on Statistical Records issued
1964 Ecumenical Periodical Exchange begun, which included fifteen Roman Catholic and twenty-one ATLA libraries
1966 Grant received from Sealantic Fund to improve professional and academic qualifications of head librarians
1968 Committee on Publication appointed
1970 Catholic seminary librarians had joined ATLA and ATLA Index representatives met with Catholic Periodical and Literature Index representatives to explore possible cooperation
1970 New constitution adopted in 1970, which had a provision for relationship to other organizations, an expansion of membership beyond AATS institutions to include accredited institutions with post-graduate theological programs, creation of the office of Executive Director, provision for chapters of the Association, and clarification of committee structure.
1970 Committee on Archives appointed to care for ATLA records; archives sent to Presbyterian Historical Society in Philadelphia; oral history program conducted
1971 Revised By-Laws adopted
1972 Board of Microtext reorganized following retirement of Raymond P. Morris and appointment of Charles Willard as chair. By 1974 there were more than 250 periodicals and 400 monographs in the microtext program
1972 Committee on Publication reorganized as a standing committee and launched two scholarly series in religion and theology - a monographic series and a bibliographic series - published by Scarecrow Press with ATLA as the sponsoring body. Kenneth E. Rowe appointed as editor of both series
1972 Reader Services Committee appointed, which operated an Instruction Clearinghouse
1973 Committee on Standards of Accreditation appointed
1973 Certificate of Incorporation and revised bylaws approved, with President Peter VandenBerge (1972-1973) as catalyst
1973/4 Second reorganization proposed by President John D. Baker-Batsel (1973-1974) with full-time staff, central office, and unified publications and communications program
1974 Ad Hoc Committee on Serials Control appointed to run pilot project on developing a union list of periodicals held by ATLA libraries; funding not found to develop permanent program but concept was referred to Bibliographic Systems Committee
1976 First volume of Religion Index Two: Multi-Author Work (RIT) issued.
1977 Periodicals Exchange Committee became the Library Materials Exchange Committee and program administered by office of Executive Secretary after 1980
1978 Subscriptions to Religion Index One (RIO), previously the IRPL, exceeded the 1,000 mark
1978 Ad Hoc Committee on the Preservation of Theological Materials appointed to investigate cooperative possibilities for storage and preservation of theological materials. Based on investigations of Andrew Scrimgeour and Charles Willard, Committee recommended program to film more than 250,000 volumes of theological materials know to be in advanced states of deterioration
1979 Board of Directors initiated an increase in dues and brought the Boards of Microtext and Periodical Indexing into closer alliance
1979-1981 President Simeon Daly (1978-1981) initiated efforts to improve communications in the Association and to improve program elements of the annual conference. Task forces proposed a number of organizational changes: production of the annual Proceedings was entrusted to editor; Recording Secretary appointed to record minutes for Board of Directors and Association; office of Executive Secretary restructured along the lines of an executive director; Program Committee created to plan annual conference
1980 Activities of Committee on Cataloging and Classification transferred to Committee on Bibliographic Systems
1980 Volume on Festschriften (1960-1969) issued, a project prepared by Elmer and Betty O'Brien
1980-1984 Lilly Foundation funded Project 2000, a study to reassess the role of libraries in theological education, headed by Stephen Peterson
1982 Retrospective project, RIT: Multi-Author Works, 1970-1975, partially supported by NEH grant published
1982 Aggressive program of microfilming added over 100 additional serials to the program
1983 Interim Board for the Preservation of Theological Monographs appointed
1984 Preservation Board created by merger of Interim Board for the Preservation of Theological Monographs and Board of Microtext: responsible for running preservation microfilming programs for serials and monographs
1984 Ad Hoc Committee on Financial Management appointed to recommend improved financial program and organizational management for ATLA; New York firm of Peat, Marwick, Mitchell and Co. (PMM) hired as consultants
1985 Indexing program restructured to provide for an Executive Director, an editor, and two assistant editors. Albert Hurd appointed as Executive Director of indexing program
1985 Robert Markham hired as full-time Director of Programs for Preservation Board
1985 Retrospective upgrading of first four volumes of IRPL published under title Religion Index One: Periodicals, Volumes 1-4 (1949-1959)
1986 PMM recommendations approved by Board of Directors; Financial Management Committee appointed; Controller employed; unified accounting system created
1986 New product, Index to Book Reviews in Religion (IBRR) developed
1987-1992 Preservation program received nine grants totaling more the $1.5 million, but program ran deficit due to recession in late 1980s and reduced subscription support from participating libraries
1988 Index Board and Preservation Board voted to work together under a Joint Executive Committee and with one Executive Director
1989 Religion Index Two: Multi-Author Works, 1976-1980, a cumulated and augmented edition, issued; index databases available online via Wilsonline system; Research in Ministry (RIM) continued in publication; Methodist Reviews Index published on contract from United Methodist Board of Higher Education and Ministry; thesaurus of index descriptors issued.
1990 Reorganization of ATLA so that Index Board and Preservation Board were placed directly under Board of Directors
1990 Pew Charitable Trust grant for three-year International Christian Literature Documentation Project
1990 Ten-year project begun to film denominationally specific materials
1991 Albert Hurd appointed chief executive officer of ATLA. This restructuring made Executive Director responsible for all staff appointments, with the Board of Directors now construed as a policy making body that vested management of the Association in the Executive Director and his/her staff.
1991 John Bollier appointed first Director of Development
1993 Three-year ATS Quality and Accreditation Project launched
Scope and Contents
The Yale Divinity School Library was designated as the official repository of the ATLA's archives in 2000. This record group consists primarily of records that had been deposited over several years at the Presbyterian Historical Society in Philadelphia, the former repository for ATLA archives. The basic series structure and organization of the records reflects the order in which materials were received from Philadelphia, though many additional records have been integrated into the sequence. The ATLA was for many years a very decentralized organization and full records were not always transferred to the archives by its scattered officers and committee chairs.
The ATLA archives in this record group are complemented by two other collections at the Yale Divinity Library: the Raymond P. Morris Papers, (RG 80) and records of the ATLA Library Development Program (RG 81). Morris, Librarian of the Yale Divinity School Library from 1932-1972, was a founder of the ATLA and long-time president of the Board of Microtext. The ATLA Library Development Program provided funds to strengthen the book collections of ninety North American theological libraries between 1961 and 1966. The program was directed by Raymond Morris, and funded by the Sealantic Fund.
Series I, Organization of the ATLA, includes records related to the formation of the Association, legal documents, and membership records. Series II, Administrative Records, includes records of various officers of the ATLA, including the Executive Secretary, Recording Secretary, Treasurer, President of the Board of Directors, and Vice-President of the Board. The quantity of records available from these various officers varies. The records related to various ATLA committees found in Series III also vary considerably in quantity and substance. Among the most complete are the records of the Cataloging and Classification Committee, which became the Committee on Bibliographic Systems. There is considerable overlap between the committee records found in Series III and other series in the collection, including the Program files of Series XIV.
Series IV provides documentation of the Board of Index from 1957 to 1988, with earlier records related to periodical indexing proposals. The Board of Microtext is documented in Series V, with minutes, reports, correspondence, and other material dating from the 1950s thourgh the 1980s. The Board of Directors records on Series VI include minutes from 1972 through 1997, as well as other correspondence and reports. These records are supplemented by the files of the various Presidents of the Board of Directors found in Series II, Administrative Records. The Board of Preservation records of Series VII continue on chronologically from the Board of Microtext records of Series V. The Preservation Board was created in 1984 by merger of the Interim Board for the Preservation of Theological Monographs and Board of Microtext, and was responsible for running preservation microfilming programs for serials and monographs.
Series VIII documents the ATLA's relationships with various other organizations, including the Association of Theological Schools in the United States and Canada. The annual conferences of the ATLA have long been a crucial part of its program. The proceedings of the conferences found in Series IX provide very detailed information about the activities and memberhip of the Association. The Publications of Series X include the ATLA News Bulletin, Bibliography Series, Monograph Series, and copies of the Religion Index. Series XI includes documentation of fellowship and scholarship programs coordinated by the ATLA as well as grant proposals for funding of ATLA activities. The Financial Records of Series XII are overview records - treasurer statements, tax reports, and the like. Series XIII, Oral Histories, is a new series, not represented in the series structure carried over from the Presbyterian Historical Society. It includes transcripts of interviews with several important leaders of the ATLA. Audio versions of some interviews are also available in Series XV, Audio-Visual Material. The records related to Programs in Series XIV also constitute a new series. The programs documented include library consulting, materials exchange, and monographs preservation. Series XV, Audio-Visual Materials, includes photographs, slides, and audio cassettes, many of them related to the annual conferences of the ATLA.
Arrangement
I. Organization of ATLA
II. Administrative Records
III. Committees
IV. Board of Index
V. Board of Microtext
VI. Board of Directors
VII. Board of Preservation
VIII. Related Organizations and Programs
IX. Conferences
X. Publications
XI. Scholarships, Fellowships and Grants
XII. Financial Records
XIII. Oral History
XIV. Programs
XV. Audio-Visual Materials
Libraries -- Special collections -- Religion; Library science -- Societies, etc.; Theological libraries -- United States; Librarians; Morris, Raymond P.; American Theological Library Association
- Organization of ATLA, Series I
  - Materials received from PHS
    - Guide to Record Group 163 prepared by Presbyterian Historical Society (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Founding of ATLA, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Guidelines for Standards of Accreditation (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Constitution (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Data for Directories, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Incorporation, 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - By-Laws relation to incorporation (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Incorporation Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Incorporation Certificates (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Job Descriptions (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Logo, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Membership Lists Sold (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Membership Lists (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Members Retired (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Seal, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Tax Exempt Status, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Directories of Past Board Members (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Personnel Handbook (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Materials added 2006
    - Certificate of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1980 (Box 122, Folder 1)
    - Legal opinion regarding legal liability of ATLA Boards, 1983 Feb (Box 122, Folder 2)
    - Corporation Trust Company - Certificate of Incorporation and correspondence, By-Laws, 1986-1989 (Box 122, Folder 3)
    - Certificate of Incorporation and Amendments, 1990 (Box 122, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence regarding ATLA Reorganization, 1990 Jul (Box 122, Folder 5)
- Administrative Records, Series II
  - Executive Secretary Records
    - Robert Beach (1947-1950)
      - Development of Standards for Theological Libraries, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Louisville Conference Preparations, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Chicago Conference Preparations, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Columbus Conference Preparations, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Correspondence regarding Constitution Revisions, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Alice Dagan (1954-1958)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Fred Cheney (1958-1965)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Thomas Camp (1965-1967)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Susan Schultz (1967-1971)
      - Notes and Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Correspondence, 1970-1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - David Wartluft (1971-1981)
      - Job Description of Executive Secretary (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Constitution and By-Laws, 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Correspondence: Council on the Study of Religion, 1972-1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence: Concordia/Seminex Discussions, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Correspondence: Association of College and Research Libraries, Committee on Continuing Education and Professional Development, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Correspondence: ATLA President, 1975-1981 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Correspondence and Grant Proposals (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Correspondence and Administrative Records (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Albert Hurd (1981-1985)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
      - Correspondence: Library Material Exchange, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence: Committees, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Simeon Daly (1985-1990)
      - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 47a)
      - Correspondence: National Humanities Alliance, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 49-50)
      - Correspondence: Board of Directors, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 52-53)
      - Correspondence: Catholic Library Association, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Report, 1988 (Box 128, Folder 2)
      - Organizational directory and job descriptions, 1983-1987 (Box 128, Folder 9)
    - Susan Sponberg (1990-1991)
      - Correspondence with Board of Directors, 1990-1991 (Box 126, Folder 28-29)
  - Recording Secretary Records
    - Margaret Whitelock
      - Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Treasurer Records
    - Harold Prince (1956-1964)
      - Correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - David Guston (1967-1971)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Warren Mehl (1971-1974)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Robert Olsen (1974-1990)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1980 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Correspondence, Notes and Reports, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Budgets and Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - President of Board of Directors Records
    - Leslie Elliott (1947-1949)
      - Correspondence, Reports, Drafts of Constitution and Membership Lists, 1945-1955 (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Reports, Minutes and Memos, 1946-1949 (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 65-67)
      - Article and obituary (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Jannette Newhall (1949-1951)
      - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 69)
      - Rochester Conference Preparations, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Raymond Morris (1951-1953)
      - Correspondence: Louisville Conference, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 71)
      - Correspondence: Evanston Conference, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 72)
      - Correspondence: Chicago Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 74)
      - Correspondence, Reports, Minutes, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 75)
      - Correspondence and Minutes, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 76)
      - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      - Correspondence: Lilly Endowment, Scholarship, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 78)
      - Correspondence and Report (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Henry Brimm
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1946-1953 (Box 7, Folder 80-81)
      - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 82)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1955-1962 (Box 7, Folder 83)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Robert Beach (1954-1956)
      - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - Correspondence: Conference, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - Correspondence and Papers: Library Education, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      - Correspondence: International Federation of Library Associations, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - Correspondence: Personal and Placement, 1954-1957, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - Correspondence: Conference, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 91)
      - Correspondence: Executive Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 92-93)
      - Correspondence: Membership, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Correspondence: Sealantic Fund, 1955-1957 (Box 8, Folder 95)
      - Proposals: Sealantic Fund, 1955-1957 (Box 8, Folder 96)
      - Sealantic Fund: Periodical Indexing and Microtext Program, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 97)
      - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 98)
      - Correspondence: Budget and Finance, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 99)
      - Correspondence: Book Exhibit, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 100)
      - Correspondence and Proposals: Grants for Microphotography, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 101)
      - Correspondence: Nominating Committee, 1956, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 102)
      - Correspondence: Executive Committee, 1956-1957, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 103)
      - Sealantic Fund: ATLA Library Development Program, 1956-1967 (Box 8, Folder 104)
      - Correspondence and Agreement: Sealantic Fund, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 105)
      - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 106)
      - Correspondence and Papers: Recruitment and Education, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 107)
      - Correspondence: Foundation Support, 1957-1959, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Helen Ulrich (1956-1957)
      - Correspondence: ATLA Constitution, 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 109)
      - Correspondence and Minutes, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 110)
      - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 111)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 112)
      - Correspondence, Minutes and Reports, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 113)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1966 (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - Kenneth Gapp (1960-1961)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 115)
      - Correspondence and Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 116-117)
      - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 118)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 119)
      - Article in Library Trends, 1960 (Box 128, Folder 7)
    - Connolly Gamble (1961-1962)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - Donn Michael Farris (1962-1963)
      - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 121)
    - Charles Johnson (1964-1965)
      - Correspondence, Reports, Constitution and Revisions, 1957-1962 (Box 9, Folder 122)
      - Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 123)
      - Miscellaneous, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 124)
    - George Bricker (1965-1966)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 125)
    - Roscoe Pierson (1966-1967)
      - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1947-1967 (Box 10, Folder 127)
      - Correspondence: Establishment of the Committee on Reprinting, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 128)
      - Recommendations: Committee on Reprinting, 1961-1966 (Box 10, Folder 129)